A Guide to the Loudoun County Fair Association 4-H Collection, ca. 1920 - 2011
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Loudoun County Fair Association 4-H Collection ca. 1920 - 2011
Thomas Balch Library
VC 0017
This collection consists of 173 photographs of various 4-H groups in Loudoun County during the twentieth century, 40 4-H Fair programs dating from 1941 to 2000, meeting minutes, flyers, correspondence, and a copy of the deed to the fairgrounds.
Loudoun Fair Association
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Loudoun Fair Association, Leesburg, VA
Alternative Form Available
Digital surrogates
Accruals
2007.0191, 2012.0165
Historical Information
Individual 4-H clubs formed around the United States during the late 1800s and early 1900s to help educate young people, ages 10 to 21, about agricultural life. In 1907 or 1908, a three-leaf clover emblem was adopted nationally, standing for head, heart, and hands. In 1911, a fourth leaf was added, standing for hustle, before being changed to mean health. The 4-H system was adopted, teaching youth how to manage farms. During the 1920s, the program organized itself on state and national levels, creating requirements for clubs, projects, and leadership. In 1927, the first National 4-H club Camp was created, making 4-H a federal-state-county organization; in that same year, state 4-H leaders adopted the national 4-H pledge and motto.
In the 1930s, 4-H projects expanded from solely agricultural in focus to include home economic projects such as clothing, child care and home management as well as agricultural engineering projects such as soil conservation and tractors. During World War II, the 4-H clubs contributed to the war efforts with community service projects for collecting scrap metal and raising victory gardens, among others. The 1950s were characterized by 4-H'ers' interest in science, as well as a lowering of the age requirements to between 9 and 19 years old. For the next 50 years, 4-H continued to grow and contribute to society by offering a learning experience for youth, as well as a social outlet. The national organization celebrated its centennial in 2002.
The first 4-H county camp in Virginia was held in Loudoun County in 1917 for tomato and canning clubs. The first Loudoun County 4-H Fair was in 1936 at the Fireman's Field in Purcellville. The annual fair was held in that spot until 1954, when it moved to the Middleburg Community Center. Two years later, the Fair moved again to Lincoln Elementary School. In 1956, Clarence R. Ahalt (1888-1962) and his wife Tillie A. Ahalt (1889-1979) donated 13 acres of land to the Loudoun 4-H organization. Since 1957, the Fair has been held on those 13 acres, located just west of Leesburg. In 1993, a 4-H scholarship program was set up by the Loudoun 4-H Clubs & Associates. The 70th anniversary of the County Fair was celebrated in 2005.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of 173 photographs of various 4-H groups in Loudoun County during the twentieth century. The photographs, taken by local photographers including Russell Gregg, Winslow William, Hugh Grubb as well as anonymous 4-H club members, feature fairs and contests, prize-winning specimens, winners and talent shows. In addition, there are photographs of 4-H'ers working on projects, playing, or participating in various camp activities. Individual photographs have been catalogued in Past Perfect, Thomas Balch Library's visual collections database.
The photographs were originally housed in "magnetic" albums, photocopies of which are included in Box 2. Photographs are arranged according to date, with undated photographs and those dated after the collection was originally organized arranged by subject at the end of the collection. There is also a folder of slides slides, primarily from the 1970s.
n addition to the photographs, the collection contains 48 programs dating from 1941 to 2011, which have been catalogued in Loudoun County Public Library's online catalogue Horizon, meeting minutes for an advisory board for Home Demonstration agents, flyers a box of catalogs handed out at the fair or included in the Loudoun Times-Mirror as a special supplement.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
"Historical Notes About 4-H Fair." Loudoun Times-Mirror, Eastern Loudoun Times. July 26, 1995, Loudoun County 4-H Fair, pg 13.
History of 4-H Clubs. http://cals.arizona.edu/aes/mac/ag-ventures/4-H_detailed_history.htm. January 23, 2010.
Loudoun County Fair Association 4-H Collection (VC 0017), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
"Loudoun 4-H Fair's Home Dates to 1957." L oudoun Times-Mirror, Eastern Loudoun Times. July 27, 1994, Loudoun County 4-H Fair, pg. 3,6.
Meadows, Bob. A Brief History of Virginia's 4-H Educational Centers. www.4-h.ext.vt.edu/camping/4hcenterhistory.html. August 16, 2010.
Other Finding Aid
Past Perfect catalogue records
Technical Requirements
Electronic media
Related Material
Russell Gregg Photograph Collection, ca. 1920-1944 (VC 0008); Winslow Williams Photograph Collection (VC 0003)
Contents List
- (VC 0017)
- (Folder 1)
  - [dancing in a field], 6 x 8"
  - Lincoln Club ... dress ..., 2.5 x 4.25"
  - 1932 (VA Tech), 2.5 x 4.25"
  - [2 girls measuring a dress hem], 2.5 x 4.25"
  - [Zack Reed with scythe, identified by Edgar Ted" Lincoln]", 8 x 10"
  - Style Dress Review held as part of 4-H Fair, 1943 or '44, 3 x 4"
  - The 1947 Loudoun County 4-H Livestock Judging
  - [6 boys with 6 cows in front of barn], 4 x 6"
  - [5 boys with 5 steers and judge], 2.5 x 4.25"
  - Virginia Delegation, 4-H Club Congress, 1950, 8 x 10"
  - Prize winning steers from the 1950 Loudoun 4-H Fair, 8 x 10"
  - Records Reap Rewards, 8 x 10"
  - Mary J 50-50 Award, $25, 8 x 10"
  - [girl winning jellyroll pan as prize], 8 x 10"
  - [boy and judge with dairy cow], 8 x 10"
  - The 4-H Clubs Welcome Hawaii and Alaska, 8 x 10"
  - Waterford Welcomes Alaskan 4-H'rs, 8 x 10"
  - Loudoun County Champion Sr. 4-H Club [persons with banner], 6.5 x 7.5"
  - [wreath making?], 8 x 10"
  - In the Swing of 4-H Work, 8 x 10"
  - Land make the Best ???, 8 x 10"
  - 1960 N-VA Dairy 4-H Show, Showing & Fitting Winners, 2.5 x 4.25"
  - [Tommy Hoff and Bobby Jeffries with steers], 8 x 10"
  - [3 boys with 4 steers -- boy with leftmost steer cut out of picture], 8 x 10"
  - [Tommy Hoff receiving award for steer], 8 x 10"
- (Folder 2)
  - [Arnetta Hubble and Jane (Virts) McCall receiving an award at the Loudoun County Four-H Fair - 1961, 5 x 7"
  - [Frankie Eppes and Mildred Crawford], 8 x 10"
  - Powell's Ft. Valley, 8 x 10"
  - State Short Course, 8 x 10"
  - Around the World with 4-H, 8 x 10"
  - [boy and girl eating watermellon], 8 x 10"
  - [unidentified 4-H members on stage], 1967, 3.1 x 3.1"
  - [unidentified teenage boy in front of 4-H banner], 5 x 7"
  - [Bluegrass band], 5 x 7"
  - [group outside at night acting], 5 x 7"
  - [falling off the horse after the jump], 5 x 7"
  - [girl showjumping], 5 x 7"
  - [breakfast], 5 x 7"
  - [Glynn Moreland], 5 x 7"
  - [The Virgina Horse Council, Inc. award recipients], 5 x 7"
  - [Certificate of Recognition -- State Honors - recipients], 5 x 7"
  - [auditorium full of people], 5 x 7"
  - [8 steer judging proofs], 8 x 10"
  - [12 steer judging proofs], 8 x 10"
  - [forestry demonstration], 8 x 10"
  - [prize-winning steer #107], 8 x 10"
  - [prize-winning steer], 8 x 10"
  - [brushing the steer prior to competition], 8 x 10"
  - [Betty Unger Crane awarding young girl a prize], 8 x 10"
  - [Carolyn Potts Grubb receiving canning award from Betty Unger Crane], 8 x 10"
- (Folder 3)
  - [judge examining a cow], 5.25 x 8"
  - [5 men in front of barn], 4 x 6"
  - [awards ceremony], 4 x 6"
  - [Kelly Traynan and bull], 1970-09, 3.5 x 5"
  - [Ronni Blake, judge, and cow], 1971-09, 3.5 x 5"
  - [contestant, judge, and cow], 1971-09, 3.5 x 5"
  - [4-H group shot], 1972, 3.1 x 3.1"
  - 1972, 3.1 x 3.1"
  - 1972, 3.1 x 3.1"
  - 1972, 3.1 x 3.1"
  - [The Loudoun County 4-H Club" display]", 1972, 3.1 x 3.1"
  - [people & horse outside building from a distance], 1972, 3.1 x 3.1"
  - [people & horse outside building -- closer], 1972, 3.1 x 3.1"
  - [4-H members], 1970s, 3.1 x 3.1"
  - [4-H members], 1970s, 3.1 x 3.1"
  - [4-H group shot], 1970s, 3.1 x 3.1"
  - [4-H group shot], 1970s, 3.1 x 3.1"
  - [4-H group shot], 1970s, 3.1 x 3.1"
  - [2 girls with scarecrow], 8 x 10"
  - [award winning steer #6 -- all brown head], 4 x 5"
  - [award winning steer -- white head], 4 x 5"
  - [award winning steer -- white head], 4 x 5"
  - [teenage boy & girl chatting, seated], 8 x 10"
  - 4-H conference [boy and girl standing outside building], 8 x 10"
  - [photography float], 8 x 10"
- (Folder 4)
  - 4-H Winners, 8 x 10"
  - 4-H'ers to Camp, 8 x 10"
  - [Actor], 8 x 10"
  - Painting Sykes Hall, 8 x 10"
  - 4-H State Winners, 8 x 10"
  - Reserve Grand Champion Steer, 8 x 10"
  - Grand Champion Market Lamb [#211], 8 x 10"
  - Reserve Grand Champion Market Lamb [#216], 8 x 10"
  - Grand Champion Steer [#6], 8 x 10"
  - Round Hill Weaving, 8 x 10"
  - I Dare You"", 8 x 10"
  - [washing a pig], 8 x 10"
  - 4-H Fashion Revue, 8 x 10"
  - Nation 4-H Horse Roundup, 198?-10-3/4, 8 x 10"
  - [photographer shooting photographer], 3.5 x 5"
  - [unidentified man in pickup truck], 3.5 x 5"
  - [boy in cowboy hat on log], 1980, 3.5 x 4.5"
  - Cromer Boys Win -- National Winner, 59th 4-H Congress, 8 x 10"
  - Mrs. Cockrell in the stand selling. 1982-10-01/02, 3.1 x 3.1"
  - Jr Camp Class, 3.5 x 5"
  - [fashion review], 3.5 x 5"
  - [girl with calf], 3.5 x 5"
  - [3 prize winners at dog show], 3.5 x 5"
  - [oratory contest contestants?], 3.5 x 5"
  - [oratory contest contestants?], 3.5 x 5"
- (Folder 5)
  - [oratory contest contestants?], 3.5 x 5"
  - [oratory contest contestants?], 3.5 x 5"
  - [fashion revue], 3.5 x 5"
  - [Market Lamb], 8 x 10"
  - [champion rabbits], 8 x 10"
  - [market lamb], 8 x 10"
  - [steer], 8 x 10"
  - [3 girls riding a horse in pyramid], 8 x 10"
  - [prize-winning pig], 8 x 10"
  - [unidentified boy showing cow], 3.5 x 5"
  - [announcer], 3.5 x 5"
  - [I heard it through the grape vine -- California Raisins], 4 x 6"
  - [girls sewing], 3.5 x 5"
  - [girls sewing], 3.5 x 5"
  - [girls sewing], 3.5 x 5"
  - [girls sewing], 3.5 x 5"
  - [girls sewing], 3.5 x 5"
  - [girls sewing], 3.5 x 5"
  - [girls sewing], 3.5 x 5"
  - [girls sewing], 3.5 x 5"
  - [girls sewing], 3.5 x 5"
  - Here I go!" [girl sewing]", 3.5 x 5"
  - [Round Hill 4-H Club blue parade truck], 3.5 x 4.5"
  - [Cloverbuds 1994], 3.5 x 5"
  - [Round Hill 4-H Club red parade truck], 3.5 x 4.5"
- (Folder 6)
  - [Talent show?], 3.5 x 5"
  - [Livestock Auction Fair 1995], 3.5 x 5"
  - [Dance/Band Fair 1995], 3.5 x 5"
  - [MC on stage], 3.5 x 5"
  - [Round Hill Robins Summer 1995], 4 x 6"
  - [contestants at tables, perhaps quiz show-type], 3.5 x 4.5"
  - [contestants at tables, perhaps quiz show-type], 3.5 x 4.5"
  - [contestants at tables, Horse Bowl 1996], 3.5 x 4.5"
  - Caring for your cat!" [presentation day 1996 - Kirsten Windle]", 3.5 x 4.5"
  - [Katie Hereford, Karen Good, Amy Windle], 3.5 x 4.5"
  - [Dance at Skyes Hall], 1996-03, 3.5 x 4.5"
  - [Learning Horse Judging at Barbara Breckett's April 1996], 1996-04, 4 x 6"
  - [June Adams (broke her arm the night before!) Dr. Stickland, Jennifer Stridd, Hunter Jenkins], 4 x 6"
  - [Horse Judging Team visits Lexington Horse Center], 1996-05, 4 x 6"
  - [panorama of 4-H exhibit hall], 4 x 6"
  - [panorama of 4-H exhibit hall], 4 x 6"
  - [panorama of 4-H exhibit hall], 4 x 6"
  - [panorama of 4-H exhibit hall], 4 x 6"
  - [panorama of 4-H exhibit hall], 4 x 6"
  - [panorama of 4-H exhibit hall], 4 x 6"
  - [panorama of 4-H exhibit hall], 4 x 6"
  - [panorama of 4-H exhibit hall], 4 x 6"
  - [panorama of 4-H exhibit hall], 4 x 6"
  - [panorama of 4-H exhibit hall], 4 x 6"
  - [panorama of 4-H exhibit hall], 4 x 6"
- (Folder 7)
  - [panorama of 4-H exhibit hall], 4 x 6"
  - [sheep and goat area outside the barn], 8 x 10"
  - [tossing bales of hay], 4 x 6"
  - [girl with steer], 4 x 6"
  - [Heman/Super Farmer contest judge], 4 x 6"
  - [adult woman, Lovettsville 4-H teenage girl, tweenie boy], 4 x 6"
  - [Flower Demonstration Skyes Hall], 1995-08, 4 x 6"
  - [6 Round Hill 4-H children sitting in a barn], 4 x 6"
  - [Hattie Ketterman & The Leaps & Bounds Horse Club helped], 4 x 6"
  - [6 Round Hill 4-H girls at a picnic table], 4 x 6"
  - [2 tweenies and a toddler], 4 x 6"
  - [WABE/Share The Fun Talent Show at Fair 1995], 1995, 4 x 6"
  - [WABE/Share The Fun Talent Show at Fair 1995], 1995, 4 x 6"
  - [Fashion Show/Luncheon for senior citizens at Loudoun Valley Community Center], 1995, 4 x 6"
  - [4-H Food Drive, Blue Ridge Bobcats at Food Lion; Thanksgiving 1995], 1995-11, 4 x 6"
  - 4-H Fair [unidentified hunt winner], 3.5 x 5"
  - [antique cars], 3.5 x 5"
  - [Caroline Graham], 3.5 x 5"
  - [group shot - County Agent Winnie Peale, Carolin Graham], 3.5 x 5"
  - [Is your life running on empty? Get a fill-up -- Join Extension Homemakers" display board]", 3.5 x 5"
  - [Joan Hager riding western style], 3.5 x 5"
  - [man riding western style, woman riding western style, possibly on a Shetland Pony], 3.5 x 5"
  - [turtle race], 3.5 x 5"
- (Folder 8)
  - [rural landscape with church], n.d, 4"x5"
- (Folder 9)
  - 81 slides 1970s
- (M 053)
- (Box 1)
  - Album 1 1990s
  - Album 2: Untitled
  - Loose Album Pages
  - Anniversary (25th) Plans
  - Awards 1955, 2002
  - Deed for Fairgrounds (photocopy) 1956
  - Journal, Advisory Board for Home Demonstration Work 1926-1947
  - Newspaper Articles
  - Publicity
  - List of cataloged programs
- (Box 2)
  - Loudoun County Annual Fair Catalogs 1978-1985; 1992; 1994-1995